An Extraordinary True Story.
Hoop Dreams is a documentary film directed by Steve James.
Every school day, African-American teenagers William Gates and Arthur Agee
travel 90 minutes each way from inner-city Chicago to St.
Joseph High School in Westchester, Illinois, a predominately white suburban
school well-known for the excellence of its basketball program.
Gates and Agee dream of NBA stardom, and with the support of their close-knit families,
they battle the social and physical obstacles that stand in their way.
This acclaimed documentary was shot over the course of five years.
Self, played by William Gates.
Self, played by Arthur Agee.
Self, played by Gene Pingatore.
Narrator (voice), played by Steve James.
Self, played by Dick Vitale.
Self, played by Bobby Knight.
Hoop Dreams is a 1994 American documentary film directed by Steve James, and produced
by Frederick Marx, James, and Peter Gilbert, with Kartemquin Films.
It follows the story of two African-American high school students, William Gates and Arthur
Agee, in Chicago and their dream of becoming professional basketball players.
Hoop Dreams was originally intended to be a 30-minute short film produced for PBS; the
filming of the special led to five years of filming and 250 hours of footage.
Hoop Dreams premiered at the 1994 Sundance Film Festival, where
it won the Audience Award for Best Documentary.
It won numerous other awards in the 1994 season, although it was not nominated for the
Academy Award for Best Documentary Feature, which led to a massive public outcry.
Despite its length (171 minutes) and unlikely commercial genre, it received high
critical and popular acclaim, and grossed over $11 million worldwide.
Hoop Dreams was ranked #1 on the Current TV special 50
Documentaries to See Before You Die.
In 2005, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The International Documentary Association's members ranked Hoop
Dreams as the best documentary of all time in 2007.
The film explores themes of chicago, illinois,
sports, narration, ghetto, college.